A Guide to the Records of the Wine Study Work Group of the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer services, 2002-2004
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Wine Study Work Group of the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, 2002-2004
The Library of Virginia
44829
1 cu. ft. (1 box)
Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred from the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, 02 February 2010.
Biographical Information
On March 29, 1877, the General Assembly passed an act creating the Department of Agriculture, Mining, and Manufacturing to compile a geological handbook, analyze soils and fertilizers, dispense information to agriculturists in the state, and distribute seeds provided by the federal government. The Board of Agriculture was established by the General Assembly on March 5, 1888, to manage the department. The name of the department was changed to the Department of Agriculture and Immigration by an act passed on February 25, 1908, and the agency was given the additional mission of promoting the immigration of farmers into the state. On March 27, 1914, the General Assembly made the commissioner of the department a member of the Convict Lime Grinding Board. This board, which supervised the employment of state penitentiary convicts at state lime grinding plants, was abolished by the state government reorganization act passed by the General Assembly on April 18, 1927, and its duties were transferred to the Board of Agriculture and Immigration.
A major shift in focus occurred when, in a statewide referendum held on November 1, 1966, the voters approved a proposed constitutional amendment passed by the General Assembly on March 11 that changed the name of the department to the Department of Agriculture and Commerce. The governor issued a proclamation of the name change on November 30, 1966, and on March 4, 1971, the General Assembly passed an act codifying the change. The name of the department was changed to the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 24, 1978.
The Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services, which oversees the department, consists of eleven members, one from each congressional district. Seven of the members must be farmers. The members are appointed by the governor for four-year terms and confirmed by the Senate. The presidents of Virginia State University and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University are ex-officio members of the board. The board is responsible for policy formulation on matters of agricultural and consumer concern.
The Virginia Wine Board was created in 1984 as part of the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services to promote the interests of vinyards and wineries in the commonwealth through research, education and marketing.
Scope and Content
Records, 2002-2004, of the Virginia Wine Study work group consist of survey results, correspondence, reports, studies and planning documents. The Virginia Wine Board Study work group is an initiative established in August of 2002 to develop strategies for the improvement and expansion of the Virginia wine industry.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Wine Study Work Group
Contents List
- Series I. Wine Study Work Group, 2002-2004., Extent: 1 cu. ft. (1 box). (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title
  - Meetings, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - ABC Winery Survey, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Background MAterials, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committee Assignments, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committee Reports, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contacts, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Economic Impact Study, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Enhancing Virginia's Grape and Wine Industry, undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Events, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial Incentives for the Wine Industry, undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Legislation, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Media, 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Report to the Governor - Draft, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Resources, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Signage, 2003-2004. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - State Wine Data, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Strategic Planning, 2002-2004. (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Tony Wolf's Wine Presentation, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tourism/Wine Marketing Partenership, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wine Demand Paper, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Wine Board Transition Task Force, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Transition, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 28)